Guide to the Lillian Cooper papers CBHM.0023
Center for Brooklyn History
- Series 3: Administrative Files, 1935 - circa 1980
  - Leaflet, etc., circa 1948 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - [Holly Point Project], 1949-1951 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Holly Point Project stationery, circa 1945 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - HPP [Holly Point Project], 1948 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé], 1947-1948 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - [Notes regarding Herman Kobbé], 1947-1948 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé], 1948 (Box 20, Folder 16-17)
  - [Notes], circa 1948 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé], 1949 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - File HK [Herman Kobbé], 1937 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - [Lists of Passengers, Siboney Ship], 1937-1938 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - File HK [Herman Kobbé], 1952- circa 1955 (Box 20, Folder 22-24)
  - [Resume], 1947 (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Older resumes, 1947-1957 (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - [Ben Cooper, Local Union No. 119 forty-year membership certificate], 1950 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - [University of Florida catalog listing], 1955-1957 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - [The New York Teachers Guild membership correspondence], 1958 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - [Expense book], 1962-1965 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - [Bread Loaf Conference correspondence], 1964 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - [Teaching evaluations], 1959-1966 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Board of Examiners [Board of Education teaching license], 1966 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - [New York City Teachers Retirement System correspondence], 1967 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - [Teaching observation report comments], 1968 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - [Handwritten will], 1969 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - [Università Italiana per stranieri certificate], 1971 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - [Writers' Summer School correspondence], 1975 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Bread Loaf [Writers' Conference], 1976-1977 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - [Hunter College class registrations and transcripts], 1977-1979 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - [Rabbi Rudin, Herzl Institute lecture notes], 1978 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - [Housing complaint], circa 1980 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - [The National Council on Aging booklet], circa 1980 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Licenses [and teaching certificates], 1930-1972 (Box 21, Folder 16, Box 24, Folder 9)
- Series 4: Herman Kobbé papers, 1935-1947
  Biographical Note
  Herman Kobbé was born on April 16, 1884. He graduated from the Columbia University School of Architecture and worked as an architect in Albany for the state of New York. Kobbé was a member of the Social Democratic Federation and ran for State Assembly a few times. In 1934, he ran for Lieutenant Governor of the State of New York on the Socialist ticket. Kobbé then maintained a private architecture practice. During World War II, he served in the United States military.
  Kobbé married Helene (Lili) Metcalfe in 1909 and they had four children together. Kobbé had many other romantic relationships, including with Lillian Cooper (from about 1935 to 1948). Kobbé remarried sculptor Selma Burke in 1949.
  Herman Kobbé died on July 21, 1966 at his home in Kingston, Jamaica.
  Series 4: Herman Kobbé papers, 1935-1947, is made up of correspondence between Herman Kobbé and his wife Helen (Lili) Kobbé (née Metcalfe) and Lillian Cooper, his partner from about 1935 to 1948. The correspondence between Cooper and Herman Kobbé represents the early days of their relationship, love letters and plans to see each other, often at their apartment at 209 Washington Park. Correspondence between Lili Kobbé and Lillian Cooper regarded Lilian's relationship with Kobbé and work that both women were involved in. Also included is a folder of documents related to Kobbé's time in Mexico (with Cooper) in 1938 and some writings and drawings by him.
  Correspondence to both Cooper and Kobbé is also included in Series 1: Correspondence. Correspondence between Cooper and Kobbé is also included in Series 3: Administrative Files.
  - [Correspondence between Herman Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], circa 1935 (Box 21, Folder 18-20)
  - [Correspondence between Herman Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1935 (Box 21, Folder 21-23)
  - [Notes and poems], circa 1935-1939 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - [Correspondence between Herman Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1936 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - [Correspondence between Lili Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1936 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - [Correspondence between Herman Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1937-1938 (Box 21, Folder 27-28)
  - [Correspondence between Lili Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1938 (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - Mexico, 1938 (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - [Correspondence between Lili Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], circa 1936 (Box 21, Folder 31)
  - [Correspondence between Sonya Kobbé (?) and Herman Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1939 (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - [Correspondence between Herman Kobbé and Lillian Cooper], 1940 (Box 21, Folder 33)
  - [Correspondence], 1940 (Box 21, Folder 34)
  - "The Chinese Box" by Herman Kobbé, circa 1940 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Drawings, circa 1945 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Sea Highway, circa 1947 (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Series 5: Photographs, circa 1905-circa 2000
  Series 5: Photographs, circa 1905-circa 2000, includes photographs of Lillian Cooper, her family, and friends. The scrapbook contains mostly photographs and photo booth snapshots of Lillian Cooper. Other photographs include both candid and professional portrait photographs of friends and family. The "Cooper-Pazeian" photographs mostly depict Lillian's sister Gertrude and her husband Hrant Pazeian's family. Many of the people in the photographs are unidentified.
  - Scrapbook, 1929-1940 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Lillian Cooper, 1938-1977 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of friends and family, circa 1905 - circa 1950 (Box 22, Folder 6-8)
  - Photographs of George and Gertrude Cooper, circa 1880-1940 (Box 22, Folder 9, Box 24, Folder 7)
    This folder has retained the title from the creator, but includes photographs of family members other than George and Gertrude Cooper.
  - Cooper-Pazeian [photographs], circa 1950s (Box 22, Folder 10-12)
  - Miscellaneous photographs [photographs of friends and family], circa 1930-circa 1945 (Box 22, Folder 13-14)
  - [Group portraits], circa 1910 - circa 1940 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - [Photographs of Gemma Cooper-Novack], circa 2000 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Kobe [Herman Kobbé photographs], circa 1935-circa 1940 (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
  - [Yeats International Summer School and University of Oxford], 1970-1971 (Box 23, Folder 5)